<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tithes a curse to all nations but Canaan, and a disturbance, and vexation to all people but the Hebrevvs. Clearly demonstrated in the case of Isaack Graye, now a prisoner, for the non-payment of tithes in the counter of great Woodstreet, London. Exposed to publick view for the discovering of the cruelties, persecutions, and oppressors of those that stand for it's maintainance.</title>
            <author>Graye, Isaac.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E809_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207598</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866639</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866639</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118916</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118916)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 123:E809[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tithes a curse to all nations but Canaan, and a disturbance, and vexation to all people but the Hebrevvs. Clearly demonstrated in the case of Isaack Graye, now a prisoner, for the non-payment of tithes in the counter of great Woodstreet, London. Exposed to publick view for the discovering of the cruelties, persecutions, and oppressors of those that stand for it's maintainance.</title>
                  <author>Graye, Isaac.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by William Larner at the Black-mores head near Fleet-Bridge, and Richard Moon at the Seven Stars in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Graye, Isaac --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118916:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Tithes A curſe to all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but CANAAN, And a diſturbance, and vexation to all people but the HEBREVVS.</p>
            <p>Clearly demonſtrated in the Caſe of ISAACK GRAYE, now a Priſoner, for the non-payment of Tithes in the Counter of great <hi>Woodſtreet, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Expoſed to publick view for the diſcovering of the cruelties, perſecutions, and oppreſſions of thoſe that ſtand for it's Maintainance.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Larner</hi> at the Black-mores head near <hi>Fleet-Bridge,</hi> and <hi>Richard Moon</hi> at the Seven Stars in <hi>Pauls Church-Yara,</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118916:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118916:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>For</hi> OLIVER <hi>Lord</hi> CROMVVELL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beſeech your favourable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect on a few rude, yet true enſuing lines; which for truth ſake makes me im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore your judicious eye; a weightier matter than uſe of conſcience cannot be, did all conſider it, I doe, and by the Almighties aſsiſtance, notwithſtanding mans power, will not flinch an inch to ſave my life: You know you have done things paſt expectation, yet be pleaſed to favour my re-minding you, that there is one above, which to ſtand in awe of him is yours, mine, and all true Chriſtians duty: in ſpeaking plain is neither falſehood nor flattery, nor I hope to your Lordſhip, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall be humbly bold to ſubſcribe my ſelf yours</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>In all Chriſtian duty,</hi> ISAACK GRAYE.</signed> An enſuing peruſall of what followes I humbly crave.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118916:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118916:3"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Intentions,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith endeavours to friends, for the delivery of a ſmall Tract enſuing, being earneſt and fervent to have truth take place, and having ſought all opportunities to have the ſame made apparently known in writing, unto <hi>OLIVER Lord CROMVVELL,</hi> before publiſhing in print, according to the uſuall cuſtome or manner, by ſuch friends as ſhould have undertaken the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for preſentation: But they upon peruſall did find the Dedication was not according to the Title he now hath, or is ſir-named by; and did thereupon reply, that it was in vain to attempt any ſuch thing; for they were certain it would not be received, becauſe it wanted his title: He now hath ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther company of friends whom I did endeavour to perſwade, as the former they adviſed me, not to addreſſe my ſelf for they were out of hopes of expectation of good, as to my relief; and therefore did diſſwade me from proſecution thereof; yet fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in my ſelf a conſcientius tye unto the Almighty and eternall JEHOVAH, who is ſole Protector, Juſtifier, Preſerver, and Pleader of the cauſe of his People againſt the enemies, the dark, blinde, ignorant powers of the world, that hates to be reformed, and that I may depart from a lying tongue, do ſpeak in and from Truth, my Conſcience bearing me witneſſe that I cannot call any man by that name; that is onely and alone due to God; neither can I appear as a flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to give unto that man a title in words, that I cannot own in conſcience: although it may prove to the loſſe of my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but I knowing the danger of flattery, that it is the mouth of flatterers that worketh ruine to him that is the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; and there upon my Lord, as I tender your everlaſting
<pb facs="tcp:118916:4"/>
welfare, I dare do no leſſe than ſpeak the truth in plainneſſe, how ever I be judged, know, I have diſcharged my duty in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this part of the Scripture, look, <hi>Prov. 16. 28.</hi> ſo in ſpeaking truth I am imboldned through the powerfulleſt, to let all ſuch as love Piety and Godlineſſe, know, that as long as I have breath, or being, I will not ceaſe my continuall ſupplications to him that made me, and the world to grant my unceſſant ſuite, in the behalfe of my ſelf, and of the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that open juſtice and right may be done to all, and that I lay open to the worlds view, in a ſhort volume, may by the Almighties bleſſing beget many within the Pale of his Church, that too long have ſate in darkneſſe, and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death; and ſhall beſeech all peruſers of the ſame, ſo to eſtimate my ſmall endeavours, as to cast a favourable and charitable aſpect of the ſame, and to reſpect the inward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, together with the outward ſubſtance, as from a friend:</p>
            <closer>Owning my ſelf to be <signed>any one of yours in brotherly affection, in anſwer to righteouſneſs, the perſecution where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath urged me to the Preſſe, that I may not lay ſilence buried in the oppreſſors hell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118916:4"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Lordſhip hath here preſented to your view, Millions of humble acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgements for the reception of an unexpected favour upon ſolicitation of precious Chriſtian Friends in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the City of <hi>London,</hi> granted to be by your ever to be Honoured ſelf to your poor then ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering ſupplicant in the <hi>Gate-houſe Weſtminſter,</hi> 1653. having remained there many moneths upon great charge, yet by your gracious favour was then inlarged and did then injoy about a moneth and odde dayes Liberty, but ever ſince <hi>April</hi> the third 1654. have again been caſt into <hi>Woodſtreet</hi> Counter <hi>London,</hi> where at preſent I remain a Priſoner, queſtioning not upon your Lordſhips peruſall of theſe my humble ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to finde as formerly; your never to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten clemency hath imboldened me the ſecond time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minde your Lordſhip for juſtice and for right from my illegall, Antichriſtian, tyrannicall impriſonment in the place aforementioned, wherein I lye and ſuffer for Chriſt and a good Conſcience, in that I dare not ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Right as to pay Tithes, and this by one <hi>Budgger</hi> of <hi>Baſſenburn</hi> in the County of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Impropriator and Tithe-renter, for which revenues of Antichriſt he hath been a cruell perſecutor of me, and my Family, and for ſome time inforced me for to forſake my poor wife and children, and relations, and to flye for <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> unto the Army of the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> for refuge, that I might have my inward peace in preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith and a good Conſcience for non-payment of Tithes: ſo through much danger and hazard of my life, through great and miraculous preſervations I returned from thence with the Army, and came up to <hi>Worceſter</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118916:5"/>
fight, and ingaged the enemies there as a Souldiour for Chriſt and his cauſe againſt Antichriſt that intereſt, and when God had given us the victory there, my life being wonderfully delivered, I gained leave to go home to my poor diſtreſſed wife and family, but becauſe this bloody antichriſtian brood of Tithe-mongers, did gape for my Liberty, I was forced, the time of my ſtaying there, to make a priſon of my houſe; and after I had been with my Family a certain time, my Adverſary <hi>Budgger</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of me at home, got up a certain company of wicked men by his appointment, and ſent them to take me, and to carry me away to priſon, who did violently break in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my houſe with their ſwords drawn, and threatning cruelly the deſtroying of my life, whereupon I was forced to defend my ſelf with ſword and piſtoll, and make my retreat into my upper Chambers; but they purſuing me with a great vehement reſolution, and threatning to pull my houſe down over my head, and to have me dead or alive, and broke ope my ſtairs foot door upon me, as alſo to raiſe the town; yet through the ſtrength of God in me, and with me, I made a ſtrong reſiſtance againſt them for ſome time, and ſo came to a Parly with them, in the mean time my diſtreſſed wife gained another ſword into her hands, and then made good the ſtairs head againſt them, whilſt I forced my paſſe out at my upper window, and ſo I ſcaped them with my life, through the exceeding goodneſſe of the Lord, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned again to the Army: but a while after I was gone to the Army, another new; a bigger company was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſent by the appointment of my Adverſary <hi>Budgger,</hi> which forced themſelves into my houſe full of envy, rage, and malice, to the great aſtoniſhment of my poor wife and children, they being alone at home; and after theſe raging wretches had rifled and ſearched my houſe to find me and could not, they returned in great heat and fury, and threatning my poor wife ſet a naked ſword to her breaſt, uſing leud and unſufferable language to her, ſtill
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118916:5"/>
threatning to kill her, if ſhe did not tell them where I was, but at length when they ſaw that they could not prevail, they left her in a very ſad condition griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly affrighted, and my poor afflicted children, ſo that upon this inhumane bloody uſage of theirs, and all for the Whore that ſits upon the cruell beaſt, my Wife fell into a great fit of ſickneſſe, which almoſt coſt her her life, yet in all the time of her fierce diſeaſe and great calamity, which did aggravate my affliction, I my ſelf durſt not ſo much as to come home to adminiſter comfort to her: for ſuch ſnares, (and privy Ambaſſadors plots and deſignes) were laid by theſe nurſed Accomplices, to take me into their mercileſſe clawes, that by the means of theſe cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, unjuſt, Antichriſtian perſecution for Tithes by the known enemies of Chriſt and his people, I have been at laſt waſted and utterly ruinated in my Families e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, above the value of four hundered pounds and upwards, by which means I am come to be much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted, and have been forced to remain as a baniſhed man from my Family, and County of my Nativity for ſome years, and have been, and am ſtill expoſed to great want, and much more miſery had faln upon me had not the mighty God raiſed me up Chriſtian Friends, in the Borough of <hi>Southwark</hi> and City of <hi>London</hi> for my relief, when I was caſt into <hi>Northampton</hi> Priſon, where I was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted for my Judgement and Conſcience in this Cauſe of Chriſt: <hi>viz.</hi> For declaring at <hi>Wellenborough</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-croſſe in <hi>Northamptonſhire</hi> againſt that Merchandiſe of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that great Prop of Antichriſt, the payment of Tithes and forced maintainance, and for the ſame I was two ſeverall dayes brought to <hi>Northampton</hi> Caſtle, and tryed at the general Seſſions of the Peace held there the firſt day I being examined upon ſeverall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories by Judge <hi>Clark,</hi> Judge <hi>Parker,</hi> and ſeverall others, as to the beſt of my remembrance their names were ſo, and little being done the firſt day againſt me, they committed me back again into Ptiſon, giving the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118916:6"/>
Gaoler a ſtrict charge for my ſafe cuſtody, and to bring me before him on the morrow, after which accordingly he did, which was the ſame day the long ſitting old Parliament was turned out of doores; I will not ſay for their wickedneſſe or oppreſſion, but leave <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to Judge; and on that day I was alſo examined up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeverall interrogatories, the which I refuſing to anſwer to, they remanded me back to Priſon again, ſaying that I had committed Treaſon, yet would they not diſcover againſt whom, nor what ſtatute or Law I had broken, although I often deſired of them to know the ſame, and without receiving any ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from them; onely they asked whether I had read <hi>Littleton</hi> or no, Becauſe I alleadged that all Statutes or moſt were made in relation to Kings: but then being no King, I could be no offender, if it could have been proved that I had broke a ſtatute: I was by their wills again ordered to be kept in priſon, untill the Aſſizes being to be held in <hi>Auguſt</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the year one thouſand ſix hundered fifty and three, but I then being a Member of the Armie, the Court Marſhall who then ſate at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> in the ſame year were pleaſed to ſend a Meſſenger of their own for me, that they might heare the cauſe before them, wherefore I was impriſoned, and have it before them, ſo that after I came to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> I did attend them certain dayes, though a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner under the cuſtody of the Marſhall Generall, and when their pleaſure was to hear me, I gave them a true Accompt of my impriſonment in <hi>Northampton,</hi> which was by a Juſtice of peace ſo called, or rather a Juſtler of Peace, who himſelf was a Tithe-monger, and in regard thereof, without ſhowing any juſt cauſe, ſent me to priſon, and for the firſt day of my hearing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Court Marſhall, notwithſtanding that I had given them a full Accompt of all my ſad ſufferings and what diſtreſſe my wife and poor Family were in by the aforeſaid devoted ſervants of Antichriſt that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118916:6"/>
yet ſome Presbyterians amongſt them, who were none of the leaſt in power and rule, were very much incenſed and imbittered againſt me, after they had heard me declare why I could not, nor ſhould not in conſcience pay Tithes, ſo that they alſo were vexed at me, and did ask me how the Miniſters ſhould live, ſo giving of them my Anſwer, they would not releaſe me that day, but gave a charge to the Marſhall to bring me before him again, in the mean time, my precious Chriſtian friends in the Borough of <hi>Southwark,</hi> hearing what hard meaſure I was like to undergo, did repair with me the laſt day of my hearing to the Court Marſhall at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> near about twenty of them, to give in their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony in my behalfe againſt the wickedneſſe and evilneſſe of paying Tithes, but they might not be permitted to come into the Court Marſhall, although by my ſelf much importuned, and ſo after they had examined me (<hi>High Commiſſion</hi> Court like) upon ſeverall interrogatories, they conſulted among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves what to do with me; and in the mean time they commanded me out of the room: And after their large conſultation, I was called in again a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and by the over-ruling power of the Presbyterian, or ridgid party amongſt them, I was diſmiſſed the Army, and ſo through the bleſſing of God became a freeman again, notwithſtanding that Collonell <hi>Pride,</hi> and other honoured friends and Officers of the Army did then oppoſe their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt me, ſo God knowes, for no other cauſe or crime was I diſmiſſed but for declaring againſt Tithes.</p>
            <p>By this, my Lord, we may ſee how men are faln: For where I did expect to have had moſt relief, there I found the moſt rigour and unkindneſſe, yet it was juſt with my God ſo to ſuffer it, that I might ſee it no good bottome to truſt in men, or upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, and uncertain arm of fleſh as I had done, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118916:7"/>
I was deceived, and did too much depart from the living God, whom I have found ſince to be my preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and Protector, bleſſed be JEHOVAH: Oh that I had been ſo guided before, for I was deceived by the flatteries of men in power, and by their fair and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious pretences, which have and did deceive me, and many thouſands, and by their not performing their Oaths, Vows, and Covenants, I am bereaved of my calling, which God did then inable me to follow, being the juſt and honeſt imployment and order which God appointed mankinde unto us from the beginning, <hi>viz.</hi> To till and manure the earth, that it may bring forth fruit unto his Creation, and this was my righteous cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and I would their callings were as righteous that have robbed and impriſoned me, although by the power of the oppreſſor I am taken there from, and by the worſt of Theeves and Robbers am deſtroyed, as my conſcience with God beareth me witneſſe that they are enemies to Chriſt and his Goſpell, ſeeing it is in meer conſcience that I cannot pay Tithes, for if I do, I ſin againſt the Light of knowledge, and ſo become an enemy to the truth of the Scripture, and ſhould thereby deny my Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, and the better hope of the Goſpel, which all they do that either pay Tithes, or take Tithes, as <hi>Heb. 7. 12. verſe</hi> doth witneſſe with me: For the prieſthood being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law, which is recorded in <hi>Deuterenomie</hi> 18. 3. verſe pointing out the then Prieſts portion, and ſaith, what ſhould be their due from ſuch a people as offered ſacrifice, whether of oxe or ſheep: that they ſhould give unto the Prieſt, the ſhoulder, and the two cheeks alſo and the maw: 4. verſe, the firſt fruits, of thy corn, of thy wine, and of thy oyle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that it doth clearly appear that there is a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Prieſthood under the Ordinance of the Law, and under the Goſpel, which did but figure out Chriſt to come in the fleſh, therefore when Chriſt the ſubſtance was come, the ſhadow was done away, as <hi>Heb.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118916:7"/>
9 8. verſe. Chap. 10. 1. doth witneſſe, <hi>Chriſt being come an high Prieſt of good things to come, by a greater and more perfect Tabernacle, not made with hands, that is to ſay, not of this building, ver.</hi> 11. 23, 24. Thus it is evident by the Scriptures, and doth plainly appear unto all thoſe who live in obedience to the knowledge of God, and doth make the Scripture their rule to walk by, and do uſe no hypocriſie, ſo as to make Religion a cloak to cover their wickedneſſe, for which if they do not, they can do no other but witneſſe with me, that to take or pay Tithes, hath and doth plainly deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, and ſo do they alſo that lend their power to force the payment and maintainance thereof: For our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our doth teſtifie and ſaith, as by the report of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>The tree is known by the fruit, for an evill tree can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring forth good fruit, neither do men gather grapes of thornes or figs of thiſtles:</hi> Therefore my Lord, if you be a reall Profeſſor of Chriſt indeed and in truth it will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appear in your actions, whilſt you have power in your hands you may appear to be for Chriſt, for it doth clearly appear that ſuch a power that forceth the payment of Tithes is not of God, but is of the Beaſt, and therefore not to be permitted, and is of the Army of Antichriſt, for they force the ſhadow or type which was but figurative to take place of the ſubſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt, and therefore take heed what you do in ſiding with, or giving forth your power; for this is the time that you wil ſhow your ſelf either to be a friend or an enemy if an enemy? then know, you deny Chriſt, and his Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip, his Redemption, Juſtification, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for Chriſt ſaith unto all his, <hi>if any man will come after me, let him deny himſelf and take up his croſſe day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and follow me, Luk.</hi> 9. 23, 24, 25, 26. verſes: <hi>for if we ſuffer with him we ſhall alſo reign with him,</hi> if we deny him he alſo will deny us, therefore once more, my Lord, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored, I beſeech you well to conſider what you do or ſuffer to be done, now you are got <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o to be chief Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of the Nation or Nations; will you permit the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118916:8"/>
permit the people of God in this nation any longer to be thus perſecuted and cruelly uſed by the means of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Laws, or rather luſts of wicked men, which tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nically compels and takes away our Liberties, Lives, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and goods, many wayes, and amongſt others by way of Tithes, and forced maintainance by Prieſts, and Impropriators, my hearty deſires to Almighty God for you my Lord, is, that your aſſiſtance be not nor ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance by thoſe oppreſſors or oppreſſing wayes which proceeds from thoſe bottomleſſe pit, locuſts and catter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillars of this Common-wealth, <hi>viz.</hi> The Armies of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, that lives by devouring, deſtroying, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning the Saints of God; My Lord, if it muſt be ſo that we muſt pay Tithes againſt our Conſcſences, let there be ſtore-houſes appointed throughout the whole Nation, that the Tithes may there be kept that the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, the fatherleſſe and the Widows may come thither to be filled within the Prieſts and Impropriators gates as was in the time of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was Judge of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and gave forth this Order which he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from God which was in the firſt Covenant a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the everlaſting Prieſthood, yet for all this know my Lord, if you do, thus, that the Prieſts and other Tithe-mongers have ſtorehouſes to put Tithes and the tenth of mens eſtates into, to fill the ſtrangers, widows, and fatherleſs withal, that there may be no beggers in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> though it be a good thing in it ſelf, yet you do but act according to the figure, &amp; own not Chriſt come in the fleſh, as I do through grace obtained in the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the truth of the Scriptures, and of the Prieſthood to be changed, and of the everlaſting high Prieſt over the houſhold of God according to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Scriptures, and therefore do I ſuffer, unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as I am, as to be a witneſſe, the ſpoiling of my goods, and Impriſonment in a joyfull Spirit; Ah, my Lord, if you would but own the report of the truth of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, you could not but acknowledge that the Prieſthood is changed, and by your Actions you would appear chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118916:8"/>
too; for Chriſt and his Cauſe which now ſuffers; Oh then, how would you own Jeſus Chriſt with his people, who witneſſeth the end of the Levitical Law and the end of the Prieſthood at whoſe Name every knee ſhould bow, and every tongue confeſſe him, for it is he that inlightens every one that cometh into the world, though ſome hate it and him, and a few love him and his, yet they that hate him ſhall one day confeſſe to their ſhame, and ſee that their deeds be evill when they have their reward, <hi>for lo, I come, ſaith he, and my reward is with me, to give to every one according to their works, whether they be good or evill; he that ſaith ſo is the Mighty King</hi> of Saints and Nations: Now my Lord, by the favour of truth, give me leave to reaſon with your Lordſhip a little according to the Scriptures: Did you ever read or hear from them that ever any was caſt into priſon for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, by thoſe that owned Chriſt, as I and others are, and my goods ſpoiled, and my Family ruinated, and left open to enemies by thoſe that did own Chriſt, as I and others are, and their goods ſpoiled, and families rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated; I am ſure the Law of God in the rigour of it, as it was delivered unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> doth not witneſſe any ſuch cruelties as I have undergone, and many in this Nation beſides my ſelf, and I am made to ſuffer for not paying Tithes, neither doth the Law of God witneſſe the taking of treeble dammages, ſurely, ſurely, my conſcience tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth me, and in the diſcharge thereof muſt declare it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that if you will not do juſtice herein, or ſuffer it to be done, ſo as to take off this murdering oppreſſing power that now is for the help of Antichriſt, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny which lyeth upon the people of God, or cry for vengeance to the Almighty, will ere long be heard ariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the poor deſpiſed, oppreſſed, and dear people of God in this Land, who are precious in the ſight of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; therefore, my Lord, while you have time, and power is now in your hands, make good your promiſe, as taking of oppreſſion from the people of God, together with a new promiſe, as I am imformed, which by you was made
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118916:9"/>
after the turning out of doors of the late laſt Parliament to diverſe ſpecial friends of the City, to wit, that if tit he were not taken off the Nation before <hi>September</hi> were out or fully ended, never truſt you more, as I hope we ſhall have no ſuch cauſe to judge of you, but that you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite your ſelf in all; and of all former and hoped not to be forgotten promiſes, as at <hi>Newmarket</hi> Heath, and <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo</hi> Heath, with ſeverall other places, what proteſtations you made there in the eyes of heaven and earth: Oh, remember, remember, the dayes of your then calamity, when you were in great diſtreſſe, with the Army of the Common wealth of <hi>England,</hi> which you were then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted withall, when you and they were in great jeopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of life, whoſe General you then were at <hi>Dumbar,</hi> and alſo at <hi>Worceſter</hi> fight, when and where my ſelf with you was ingaged, and at ſeveral other places which you may remember, did not we all there declare for Chriſt King of his Saints, and have not all your pretences then and ſince as before been to take off oppreſſion tyranny and abſoluteneſſe, and for this very cauſe expreſſed, we reſt in hope that the ſtrength of God may cauſe you to yield obedience ſo far to deny your ſelf, as in anſwer to that bleſſed Scripture which gives a good report of the words of our Saviour Chriſt, for <hi>I was hungry and ye gave me meat, I was thirſty, and ye gave me drink naked &amp; ye cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, in priſon and ye viſited me, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo far as you are found performing the work of the Lord, the anſwer of the King to you will be, for as much as you have done it to one of theſe my Brethren, you have done it unto me, whoſe bleſſed example my deſires are unto God for you that you may follow, ſo humbly taking leave of you, my Lord, I</p>
            <closer>Devote my ſelf <signed>yours ſo far as you are Chriſts, <hi>ISAACK GRAYE.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt the</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1654.</date>
From my burdedſome, oppreſsive, illegall, antichreſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and tyrannicall impriſonment in great <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet</hi> Counter, <hi>London,</hi> the place of my preſent captivity.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
